[MUSIC]
There are two general ways that
fragments get added to activities.
First, they can be statically
added to the activity.
For example, by putting them
into the activity's layout file,
which is then used in
a call to setContentView.
Alternatively, you can add fragments
problematically using the FragmentManager.
However they get added though,
once they're added,
Android will make a call to onCreateView.
And within onCreateView,
the fragment can use its own XML layout,
similar to what activities do
when they call setContentView, or
they can programmatically
build their user interfaces.
And again, however it's done,
once the user interface view is built,
onCreateView must return the view that's
at the root of its user interface layout.
And that view will eventually be
given to the hosting activity and
added to the hosting
activity's user interface.
So, let's look back at
the FragmentStaticLayout application and
see how it defines its layout.
Here's the application again.
And as you remember, there's a panel
on the left showing the play titles and
there's a panel on
the right showing quotes.
And each of these panels is
implemented by a different fragment,
one is called TitleFragment and
the other is called QuoteFragment.
And this application's main activity
is called QuoteViewerActivity.
Let's open up the QuoteViewerActivity
file and see how it handles or
creates its layout.
Now first,
you see that in the onCreate method,
there's a call to setContentView with
the parameter value R.layout.main.
So let's look in the res/layout
directory for the file called main.xml.
And here it is and let me open it up.
As you can see, the entire layout
is comprised of something called
a LinearLayout and
that LinearLayout contains two fragments.
And inside those Fragment tags,
there's an attribute called class.
And the value of this
attribute is the name of
the class that implements that fragment.
So in this case, one fragment is
implemented by the TitleFragment class and
the other is implemented by
the QuotesFragment class.
Anyway, that's enough for now.
We'll talk more about layouts
when we get to user interfaces.
In any event, when this XML file is read,
Android will understand that it needs
to create these two fragments and
that it needs to install them
in the QuoteViewer activity.
And this will start the chain of lifecycle
calls that we talked about earlier.
And as I said, one of those calls
will be a call to onCreate view,
in which the fragment is responsible for
creating its user interface layout.
Let's take a look at one of those layouts,
the one in QuoteFragment,
to see how it creates its user interface.
Now here's the QuoteFragment class and
down here is its onCreateView method.
This method calls the inflate
method of the LayoutInflater class,
passing in a layout file as a parameter,
and
the effect of this is pretty similar
to what happens in setContentView.
Specifically, an XML file is read in and
converted into Java objects corresponding
to some user interface views.
You can also add fragments to an activity
without hardcoding the fragments into
the activity's layout file.
And to do that, while the activity is
running, you have to do four things.
One, get a reference to
the FragmentManager.
Two, begin a FragmentTransaction.
Three, add a Fragment to the activity.
And four, commit the FragmentTransaction.
Now to see this in action, let's take
the FragmentStaticLayout application and
change it a bit so that the fragments
are added programmatically rather
than being added as part,
as part of the QuoteViewer's layout file.
Now here we are back in the IDE.
I've created a new application called
FragmentProgrammaticLayout and
it's supposed to look exactly
like FragmentStaticLayout.
The only difference is how the fragments
get added to the main activity.
Let's open up the QuoteViewerActivity and
see how it handles its layout.
Now here in onCreate,
there's a call to setContentView with
a parameter value R.layout.main.
So let's look in the res/layout
directory for that main.xml file.
Now here it is.
Let me open it up.
Now as you can see, the entire layout is
again a LinearLayout with two subviews.
But instead of it being,
the subviews being fragments, this time,
the subviews are frame layouts.
The frame layout is to essentially reserve
some space in the user interface and
we'll fill the space in later when we
add the fragments to this activity.
Now, let's go back to the onCreate
method of QuoteViewerActivity.
Now we'll walk through the steps of
adding the fragments into the user inter,
into the activity.
And just like I said earlier,
there are four steps.
First, we get a reference
to the FragmentManager.
Then we call the beginTransaction
method on the FragmentManager.
And that returns a FragmentTransaction.
Next, we call the add method of the
FragmentTransaction, passing in an ID for
the frame layout and passing in
the fragment that that view will hold.
And we'll do that for both the
TitleFragment and for the QuoteFragment.
And finally, we'll call the commit
method on the FragmentTransaction.
Now, let's run the code and make sure
that we haven't goofed anything up.
And here's the FragmentProgrammaticLayout
application running on an emulated tablet.
And it seems to operate as promised.
So, now we know how to add fragments
to an activity programmatically.
But in our example,
it didn't really make that much
difference in the sense that even though
we added the fragments programmatically,
the layout itself was static.
There are always exactly two panels and
that never changes.
Now, one of the nice things about being
able to add fragments on the fly,
however, is that it allows you
to dynamically change the user
interface while the program is running.
And if you do this right,
it allows you to make good use
of your precious screen space.
So, let's take a look at a simple example
that gives you a little flavor of
this dynamic user interfaces.
I'll launch an application called
FragmentDynamicLayout, which, again,
is similar to the previous examples,
but sometimes it
will show a single fragment and
sometimes it will show multiple fragments.
So here the application,
we've just started it up and
it's showing a single fragment.
It's showing the TitleFragment and
nothing else.
And in fact, you can see here that I've
changed the title of Hamlet to make it
a little longer and
you see that it takes up much more
of the screen space than before.
And in addition, if I click on that title,
you can see that the item is
indeed taking up the whole,
the entire screen horizontally.
Now that I finished clicking
on the title though,
you can see the familiar
quote from Hamlet.
And at this point, the application
is displaying two fragments.
If I now hit the Back button,
you see that we've gone back to
having just a single fragment.
So let's take a look at the source code.
Now here I am back in the IDE.
And I'll open up
the FragmentDynamicLayout application.
And we'll take a look at
the QuoteViewerActivity file.
Now first,
here's the call to setContentView,
passing in the main.xml file.
And this is pretty similar
to what we saw before.
Next, we'll start the process of
adding a fragment to this activity.
This time, however,
we'll only add the TitleFragment.
In fact, we'll only ever add
the quote fragment if the user
indeed clicks on a title.
Now, supposing the user
does click on the title.
The onList selection method
will then be called.
Now let's take a look at that method.
First, we'll test to see if
the quote fragment has already been
added to the layout.
And if it hasn't, then we'll add it now
by starting another FragmentTransaction.
So, two things are new here.
First, we're going to add this
transaction to the task back stack.
And that way, when the user
hits the Back button, we'll go
back to the one fragment layout that we
had before it was, before it was added.
And we have to do this because,
by default, fragment changes
are not tracked by the back stack.
The second new thing is that at the end,
I've added a call to
FragmentManager.executePendingTransacti-
ons.
And this forces the transaction
to be executed immediately,
rather than at some later time when
the system finds it convenient to do so.
And again, I have to do this because
otherwise, Android might, it might take,
you know, god knows how long before
it actually updates the display.
Now, if you remember back to our lesson
on the Activity class, I talked about
how activities can handle configuration
changes manually using methods
such as onRetainNonConfigurationInstance
and getLastNonConfigurationInstance.
And at that time, I mentioned that those
methods were deprecated in favor of
other methods in the Fragment class.
So let's talk about those methods now.
Now, if you're using a fragment and
the device's configuration changes,
then Android, by default, will kill
the hosting activity and recreate it,
just like we talked about before.
However, if you call the setRetainInstance
method on the fragment,
passing in the value true as a parameter,
then when configuration changes occur,
Android will kill the activity, but not
destroy the fragments that it's hosting.
Instead, it will save
that fragment state and
it will detach the fragment
from the activity.
And in addition,
it won't destroy that fragment and so,
it won't recreate it later when
the hosting activity is recreated.
And as a result, the fragment will not
receive calls to its onDestroy method nor
to its onCreate method.
Let's take a look at
another example application that
demonstrates this behavior.
This application is called
FragmentStaticConfigLayout and
its functionality is the same
as the previous examples.
The difference here though,
is that I've added some code to
handle configuration changes.
Now, when the device is in landscape mode,
the layout is basically what we've seen so
far.
Both fragments use the large font of 32sp,
or scale-independent pixels.
The TitleFragment takes about
a third of the horizontal space,
while the QuoteFragment takes
the remaining two-thirds of the space.
And if a title is too long to fit on
a single line in the TitleFragment,
that text will simply wrap
around to a second line.
When the device is in portrait mode,
however, the layout changes a bit.
Both fragments use a smaller 24sp font and
the TitleFragment takes up only
a fourth of the horizontal space,
while the QuoteFragment takes up
the remaining three-quarters of the space.
And if a title is too long to fit on
a single line in the TitleFragment,
then that title will still be
limited to a single line and
we'll just replace some of
the text with ellipses.
Let's see that application in action.
I'll start the application with
the device in landscape mode.
I'll select one of
the title to show a quote.
And as I said, the TitleFragment and
QuoteFragment will use larger fonts.
They're dividing up the screen in a
roughly one-fourth to three-fourths ratio.
And in the TitleFragment,
it's allowing the title of Hamlet
to spill over onto a second line.
Now, let's rotate the device.
Now, one thing that you notice is that
even though Android has killed and
restarted the QuoteViewerActivity,
the title that I
previously checked is still checked, and
that's because I made sure to call
setRetainInstance true in both fragments.
So, information, for
example, information about which
item was checked, has been retained.
And we'll see how that's
done in just a second.
You'll also notice that now that we're in
portrait mode, the layout has changed.
In fact, the fonts are smaller now and
instead of that Hamlet title spanning two
lines, the end of the title has
been replaced with ellipsis.
So, let's go see how this
look works in the code.
Now here, I've opened
the FragmentStaticConfigLayout application
in the IDE.
Next, I'll open up
the TitleFragment.java file.
And as you can see,
this code is mostly the same as what we
saw in the other example applications,
but there are at least two differences.
Let's look at those.
The first difference is
in the onCreate method.
I've added a call to setRetainInstance,
true.
And again, this means that when
configuration changes occur,
Android will not kill this fragment.
The second difference is in
the onActivityCreated method.
And right here at the end,
I've added some code that checks to
see whether m current index
is not equal to minus 1.
And if that's true, it means that the user
has previously selected a title and so,
this call to onActivityCreated
is probably occurring because of
a configuration change.
So in this case, we want to make sure
that that title remains checked.
Now, now I made similar changes to
the QuoteFragment class as well.